Guide to the Nicole Baran Papers SC1269
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2015-156
  - MSW (Domestic Violence Related), 2002-2003; Series 36
    Baran attended the George Warren Brown School of Social Work from 2002-2003 in order to study teen dating violence. She ended up studying Domestic Violence more broadly. She had a concentration in women's issues and specialized in management. Tonya Edmond, Meg Schnabel and Cathy Blair served as influential mentors.
    - Baran's Research Paper and Research Articles
      These are Baran's research papers and the articles used to inform them.
      - Domestic Violence Paper/Dating Violence (Box 26)
        Includes articles.
      - Project H.A.R.T. (Box 26)
        This was the teen dating violence prevention program that Baran analyzed for Dating Violence paper above.
      - Mandatory/Dual Arrest Paper (Box 26)
        "Mandatory Arrest Laws: The Catch-22 for Victims of Intimate Partner Violence" and articles.
      - Couples Counseling - DV, 2003 (Box 26)
        PowerPoint presentation: "The Controversy Over Couples Counseling" and articles.
    - MSW Domestic Violence Course
      - Domestic Violence Class, 2003 (Box 26)
        This is the Domestic Violence course taught by Meg Schnabel and Cathy Blair that served as the original foundation for constructing the course on VAW at Stanford.
      - Course Reader (Box 26)
      - Meg's Domestic Violence Presentation (Box 26)
        This folder includes the original presentation by Meg Schnabel from the MSW DV Course.
    - MSW Student Group Baran Started
      Baran started the first Violence Against Women Awareness group at George Warren Brown School of Social Work. It still exists as of 2014. The intent, in part, was to ensure that all social work students received education on DV, which was not happening at the time.
      - Violence Against Women Awareness Group (Box 26)
    - MSW Practicum Redevelopment Opportunities for Women (ROW)
      Baran's practicum job with ROW included REAP, the IDA program, Board Intern and Greenbook Committee, which led to her being hired to write the guidelines for the state of MO for Domestic Violence advocates on the co-occurrence of Domestic Violence & CM.
      See Box 18 for related materials.
      - ROW documents (Box 26)
      - ROW Policy Manual (Box 26)
      - MCADomestic Violence Greenbook Committee (Box 26)
        See Box 18 for Baran's MSW Needs Assessment paper which included the focus group that led to her first draft of the Guidelines for Domestic Violence advocates on co-occurrence of Domestic Violence and CM.
      - ROW Meetings (Box 26)
      - REAP (Box 26)
        Baran taught financial literacy to battered women.
      - IDA Program – Economic Self-Sufficiency (Box 26)
      - Practicum Notes (Box 26)
      - Patient Packet Missouri: AWARE Hotline (Box 26)
        Baran volunteered on hotline.
      - Domestic Violence Presentation (Box 26)
        This folder includes the first presentation Baran made on behalf of ROW. Includes handwritten notes.
    - YWCA St. Louis SART (Sexual Assault Response Team) Training Manual
      Baran was a volunteer on the emergency Sexual Assault Response Team.
      - YWCA St. Louis SART (Sexual Assault Response Team) Training Manual (Box 26)
    - St. Louis Court Watch
      Courtwatch was a team of Domestic Violence advocates that observed judges in action in Domestic Violence cases and made recommendations. Baran was a volunteer in 2003. This would be useful for someone wanting to start a courtwatch in their community. This is where Baran heard a judge state "I would hit her too if that was my wife" under his breath.
      - Court Watch Manual and Training (Box 26)
    - Practicum Conferences
      - Housing Policy and Practice, 2003 (Box 26)
      - MCADomestic Violence Annual Conference, 2003 (Box 26)
      - MCADomestic Violence Training (Box 26)
      - MCADomestic Violence St. Louis Domestic Violence 101 (Box 26)
      - MCADV: And Justice for All: Court Advocacy with Victims of DV Training (Box 26)
  - MSW (Domestic Violence Related Women’s Issues), 2002-2003; Series 37
    Includes articles for the course and papers, lectures. Includes handwritten notes in most folders.
    - Social, Economic and Political Sum, 2003 (Box 24)
    - Human Behavior (Box 24)
    - Human Behavior Handouts (Box 24)
    - Human Behavior Paper Articles (Box 24)
      Includes paper entitled "Social Learning Theory and Feminist Theory: What They Tell About Woman Battering." See Graded Papers for paper.
    - Personnel Management (Box 24)
    - Personnel Mngment (Box 24)
    - Organizational Behavior (OB) (Box 24)
    - OB Paper (Box 24)
    - Marketing Sum, 2003 (Box 24)
    - Human Diversity (Box 24)
    - Law for Social Workers (Box 24)
    - Social Welfare Policy Class (Box 24)
    - Policy Paper (Box 24)
      Policy Brief Written on VAWA. Includes articles and notes on articles. See Graded Papers.
    - Policy Brief #3 (Box 24)
    - Interventions with Women (Box 24)
      Course taught by Tonya Edmond. Includes paper entitled “He Sort of Inserted Himself in my Mind: A Feminist Critique of Dialogues with Mad Women.”
    - Interventions w/ Women (Box 24)
      Includes paper entitled “Community Collaboration Project, Women’s Support and Community Services: Project H.A.R.T., Healthy Alternatives for Relationships among Teens.”
    - Women's Issues 1, 2003 (Box 24)
      Includes reading journal.
    - Women's Issues 2, 2003 (Box 24)
    - Prostitution Paper (Box 24)
      Includes articles for the paper entitled “Empowered or Oppressed? The Feminist Debate on Prostitution: Who’s Left Behind?”
    - Foundation I Paper - Economic Self-Sufficiency (Box 24)
      This is the research and the paper entitled “Economic Self-Sufficiency for Battered Women: An Idea in Progress.” See Graded Papers.
    - Graded Papers Fall, 2002 Fall (Box 24)
      Includes "Economic Self-Sufficiency for Battered Women: An Idea in Progress," "Policy Brief of Violence Against Women Act (Continuation)," "Social Learning Theory and Feminist Theory: What They Tell About Woman Battering," Empowered or Oppressed? The Feminist Debate on Prostitution: Who's Left Behind?"
    - Graded Papers, 2003 Spring (Box 24)
      Includes "The Intersection Between Workplace Safety and Work/Life Balance: The Impact of Domestic Violence," "Safety Plan Reaction Paper," "Domestic Violence Reading Log #1," "Domestic Violence Reading Log #2," Organization Assessment: Redevelopment Opportunities for Women, Inc.," "Domestic Violence Training and Child Protection Services: A Research Proposal," "Dating Violence Education: The Prevention Dilemma"
    - Service Utilization Article (Box 24)
      Tonya Edmond asked Baran to co-write an article entitled "Access to and Utilization of Services by Abused Women: An Analysis of the Impact of PTSD and Depression." Article missing from archive.
    - Research Methods (Box 24)
    - Research Proposal, 2003 (Box 24)
      This is the proposal that led to the initial research for the Evaluation of Programs and Services course Needs Assessment paper that led to the publication by Baran of the guidelines entitled "Helping Battered Women and Their Children: A Guide for Domestic Violence Advocates on the Co-Occurrence of Domestic Violence and Child Maltreatment."
      Includes graded proposal introduction and literature review.
  - MSW (Other), 2002-2003; Series 38
    - Washington University in St. Louis, George Warren Brown School of Social Work: Student Handbook, 2002-2003 (Box 27)
    - Calendar Book, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Practicum Possibilities (Box 27)
    - Budgeting/Accounting (Box 27)
    - Budgeting/Accounting (Box 27)
    - Evaluation of Program and Services (Box 27)
      This is the course where Baran wrote "A Needs Assessment: Domestic Violence Service Providers Response to CM" that led to the publication by Baran of the guidelines entitled "Helping Battered Women and Their Children: A Guide for Domestic Violence Advocates on the Co-Occurrence of Domestic Violence and Child Maltreatment."
      See Box 18 for paper and focus group documents.
    - Foundations I (Box 27)
    - Foundations II Class (Box 27)
    - Foundations II Articles (Box 27)
  - Electronic Records, Series 39; 21 megabyte(s); 5 computer files (pdf)
    - Baran CV. 8.25.15 redact.pdf, 2015 Aug 25; Baran CV_ 8_25_15 redact_pdf; 1 computer files (pdf)
      Series 1, Memorabilia Binder: Nicole Baran resume.
    - Memorabilia Binder Inventory.pdf, 2015; 1 computer files (pdf)
      Series 1, Memorabilia Binder: Table of Contents
    - NB Office Library Inventory.pdf, 2015; 1 computer files (pdf)
      Series 1, Miscellaneous Memorabilia--Office Library Bibliography - Books and Media--Office Library - Books.
    - NB Office Media Inventory.pdf, 2015; 1 computer files (pdf)
      Series 1, Miscellaneous Memorabilia--Office Library Bibliography - Books and Media--Office Library – Media.
    - WCC Leadership 4.5.14.pdf, 2014 Apr 5; 1 computer files (pdf)
      Series 1, Memorabilia Binder: Speaking Truth & Moving Sand: Why It Matters